Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, Department of Justice, 1975-1977; VIII.
  - Events, 3.
    - Cleveland Chapter of the Federal Bar Association, Cleveland, OH, June 8, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 20)
    - Crime Prevention/Preservation of Order Luncheon, Aberdeen Proving Ground, MD, June 9, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 21)
    - Criminal Law Section of the State Bar of Wisconsin, Fontana, WI, June 18, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 22)
    - Virginia State Bar, Alexandria, VA, July 9, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 23)
    - Albuquerque Chamber of Commerce General Membership Meeting, Albuquerque, NM, July 20, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 24)
    - Controlled Substance Conspiracy Conference, Minneapolis, MN, July 22, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 25)
    - "Good Morning America" Appearance, New York, NY, July 26, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 26)
    - Better Government Association Membership Luncheon, Chicago, IL, August 6, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 27)
    - American Bar Association Judicial Administration Division's Joint Luncheon, Atlanta, GA, August 7, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 28)
    - Federal Bar Association Annual Conference, Washington, D.C., September 16, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 29)
    - Pittsburgh Federal Executive Board Luncheon, Pittsburgh, PA, September 24, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 30)
    - National Institute of Municipal Law Officers Annual Meeting, Las Vegas, NV, October 12, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 31)
    - Annual Federal Law Enforcement Dinner, Grand Rapids, MI, October 21, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 32)
    - "America Remembers," Veterans Day, Arlington National Cemetery, VA, October 25, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 33)
    - Yale Law School Advisory Conference on White Collar Crime, Mt. Kisco, NY, October 29, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 34)
    - American Bar Association Luncheon, Washington, D.C., November 1, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 35)
    - Blair County Bar Association, Hollidaysburg, PA, November 5, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 36)
    - Allegheny County League of Women Voters Luncheon "Man of the Year Award" to Judge Maurice B. Cohill, Pittsburgh, PA, November 12, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 37)
    - Conference Board's International Council, New York, NY, December 2, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 38)
    - WJAC "Viewpoint" Discussion of "Effective Law Enforcement," Johnstown, PA, December 3, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 39)
    - American Trucking Associations, Inc., Security Council, Arlington, VA, December 7, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 40)
    - Federal Law Enforcement Association, New Orleans, LA, December 9, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 41)
    - Pennsylvania Society Annual Dinner, New York, NY, December 11, 1976 (Box 49, Folder 42)
    - Attorney General's Annual Awards Ceremony, Washington, D.C., December 14, 1976 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Manassas Rotary Club, Manassas, VA, December 15, 1976 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Prosecutor's Institute DE Law School of Widener College, Wilmington, DE, January 11, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Securities Industry Association, New York, NY, January 14, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - President's Commission on Whitehouse Fellowships, Washington, D.C., January 18, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Housing and Urban Development (HUD): Justice Seminar on Program Abuse, Quantico, VA, March 2, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - National Flexible Packaging Association, West Palm Beach, FL, March 25, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Invitations to Events, 1975 - 1977 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 4.
    Folders are arranged chronologically although some folders contain correspondence that is arranged in reverse chronological order. Of special note is one folder of Thornburgh's correspondence as Acting Deputy Attorney General (February 8, 1977-March 11, 1977).
    - Correspondence Regarding Appointment as Assistant Attorney General, 1975-1977 (Box 50, Folder 9-13)
    - Correspondence from Thornburgh, July 14, 1975-February 11, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 14-17)
    - A-D, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 18)
    - E-H, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 50, Folder 19)
    - I-L, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - M-P, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Q-S, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - T-V, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - W-Z, July, 1975-March, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with American Civil Liberties Union regarding Grand Jury Interrogation by the FBI, April, 1976 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence as Acting Deputy Attorney General, February 14, 1977-March 11, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence Regarding Wire Tap Authorization, October 17, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - Jim Seif's Files, 5.
    These are Seif's "reading files," consisting of correspondence and memoranda to and from Jim Seif, Special Assistant to AAG Thornburgh, as well as a few files to and from Thornburgh himself. These reading files are arranged chronologically. There is also a folder containing FBI-related materials, such as booklets, pamphlets and other relevant articles, including one about J. Edgar Hoover. The Criminal Division Report by Seif and Waldman will be found in the AAG's files, dated November 18, 1975.
    - Correspondence and memoranda to and from Seif and AAG Thornburgh, July, 1975-April, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 9-11)
    - Memoranda and notes, U.S. Department of Justice, Criminal Division, 1975-1976 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - FBI articles, booklets, magazines, and FBI Director Clarence M. Kelley speech, "Perspectives of Power", 1973-June, 1976 (Box 51, Folder 13)
  - Assistant Attorney General Thornburgh's Files, 6.
    These chronological files consist of a variety of Criminal Division files that the Assistant Attorney General kept for convenience and reference. The folders begin with Thornburgh's appointment as Assistant Attorney General and extend to his brief time as Acting Deputy Attorney General, and even Acting Attorney General, in February and March of 1977. Notably, within these files, are: Thornburgh's work on the Criminal Division Strike Forces, Thornburgh's Criminal Division Reports to the Attorney General and Thornburgh's invaluable staff and personal notes.
    - Appointment as Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, 1975 (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Thornburgh Bios and one for Ginny Thornburgh, 1975 (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - The United States Senate Report of Proceedings Hearing held Before the Committee on the Judiciary: Nomination of Richard L. Thornburgh to be Assistant Attorney General, volumes 1 and 2, Washington, D.C., June 12, 1975 (Box 51, Folder 16)
    - "Criminal Division," by James Seif and Jay Waldman, November 18, 1975 (Box 51, Folder 17)
    - Thornburgh Notes on Criminal Division Topics and To Do Lists, 1975-1976 (Box 51, Folder 18)
    - Schedules of Department Activities, 1975-1977 (Box 51, Folder 19)
    - Structural organization of the Criminal Division, 1975-1977 (Box 51, Folder 20)
    - Report to the President by the Commission on CIA Activities within the United States, June, 1975 (Box 51, Folder 21)
    - Criminal Division Reports to the Attorney General, December 16, 1975-January 28, 1977 (Box 51, Folder 22)
    - Pennsylvania Crime Commission, Department of Justice, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, Report: A Study of the Quality of Law Enforcement in Liberty Borough, 1975 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Remarks of the President to the California State Legislature (annotated), September 5, 1975 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Supreme Court of the United States Briefs nos. 75-313 (Mazzei) and 75-6521 (Abney), October, 1975 and October, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Thornburgh's Investigation into the Testimony of Mr. Kearns regarding Insider Trading, October, 1975 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Pennsylvania Bar Association, 1975-1976 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Federal Bar Association, 1975 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - American Bar Association, 1975-1976 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - American Bar Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Public Integrity Section, 1975-1977 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Western District of Pennsylvania, 1975-1977 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Judiciary Committee Research on Grand Jury Reform (S.3274), 1975-1977 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Tax Reform, 1975-1977 (Box 52, Folder 12-13)
    - Guidelines for Prosecutors on Prosecutorial Discretion, 1975-1977 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Field Circuit Units, 1975-1977 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - Materials Regarding the Department of Justice's purported targeting of Mayor Frank Rizzo, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - United States Department of Justice Legal Activities (annotated), 1976 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Criminal Division: Major Fraud Section Activities, December, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - Materials Regarding the Testimony of Sidney T. Walker before the Federal Power Commission Judge, 1976 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Report of the Department of Justice Task Force to review the FBI's Martin Luther King, Jr., Security and Assassination Investigations, January 11, 1977 (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - State Department Luncheon regarding Mexico, February, 1977 (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - "White Collar Crime: Nuts and Bolts," unpublished Op. Ed submitted to the New York Times, February-March, 1977 (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Reports of the Accomplishments of the Criminal Division, 1977 (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - Assistant Attorney General's resignation, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Acting Deputy Attorney General, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Affidavit regarding Nicholas Gage New York Times Article, May, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Magazine Articles regarding the Supreme Court (annotated), 1967-1977 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Memoranda, July 14-December 31, 1975 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Justice Department clippings and articles, 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Investigation of Former Office of Management and Budget Director, Bert Lance, 1976-1979 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda, 7.
    Folders here are arranged chronologically. The memoranda primarily are from Thornburgh to other members of the Department of Justice. The remainder are to Thornburgh from his staff members. Two files of note are: "Review of the Criminal Division" and one of memoranda from Thornburgh as Acting Deputy Attorney General (February 8-March 11, 1977).
    - Memoranda from Thornburgh, January 1, 1976-February 11, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 8-10)
    - Memoranda to Thornburgh, 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Memoranda from Thornburgh to Criminal Division, 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Memoranda from Thornburgh to Attorney General, 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Review of the Criminal Division to Jay Waldman and Jim Seif from Thornburgh, November 18, 1975 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Memoranda as Acting Deputy Attorney General, February 14-March 11, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 15)
  - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 8.
    Folders are arranged chronologically and contain articles and newspaper clippings from 1975-1977, many of which Thornburgh underlined and annotated. These articles and clippings are maintained in three categories: political, criminal justice, and crime and corruption.
    - Article on politics (annotated), 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 16)
    - Criminal Justice Issue Clippings (annotated), 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 17)
    - Clippings and Articles on Crime and Corruption (annotated), 1975 - 1977 (Box 53, Folder 18-19)
  - Calendars and Telephone Logs, 9.
    The calendar folders are chronological and consist of the pages from Thornburgh's office page-a-day calendar. Entries include professional, social and family obligations. The telephone logs are spiral bound notebooks that record incoming and outgoing telephone calls made from the Assistant Attorney General's office. Information included in the logs is: the time of call, with whom Thornburgh spoke and whether it was an incoming or outgoing call. Also included is the Acting Deputy Attorney General's telephone log. The telephone memos consist of Thornburgh's outline of topics covered during phone conversations as well as the time, date and with whom he spoke.
    - Daily Calendar Pages, 1975-1977 (Box 53, Folder 20-21)
    - Telephone Logs from Thornburgh as Assistant Attorney General, July, 1975-February, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 1-2)
    - Telephone Log from Thornburgh as Deputy Attorney General, February 11, 1977 - March 11, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Thornburgh's Notes of Telephone Conversations, 1975-1977 (Box 54, Folder 4-6)
  - Court Cases, 10
    Folders are arranged chronologically and contain court opinions and final judgments from court cases. As Assistant Attorney General, Thornburgh kept tabs on situations and investigations with which he had interest from his time as the United States Attorney of Western Pennsylvania.
    - United States Court of Appeals, Third Circuit: United States vs. Frank Mazzei, Western PA, May 8, 1975 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Third Circuit: United States vs. Frank C. Hilton, Western PA, 1975 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Third Circuit: United States vs. Joseph Sica, Western PA, April 6, 1976 (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - United States District Court for the Western District of Pennsylvania: United States vs. George J. Mowod, 1976 (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - United States District Court for the Northern District of Ohio, Eastern Division: United States vs. Jack Payner, 1976-1977 (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Tenth Circuit: United States vs. Cameron David Bishop, CO, May, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Court of Common Pleas of Delaware County, PA: Robert E.S. Curran vs. The Philadelphia Inquirer, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Department of Justice Files, 11.
    Folders are arranged chronologically and include materials about: Blair A. Griffith, U.S. Attorney of Western Pennsylvania, Attorney General Edward H. Levi and Attorney General Griffith Bell. The two Annual Reports of the Attorney General included in this subseries are in book form.
    - Press Releases: Blair A. Griffith, U.S. Attorney for Western PA, July, 1975-April, 1976 (Box 54, Folder 14)
    - Annual Report of the Attorney General of the United States, 1975-1976 (Box 54, Folder 15-16)
    - Articles and Speeches: Attorney General Edward H. Levi, 1975-1977 (Box 54, Folder 17)
    - Articles and Speeches: Attorney General Griffin Bell, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 18)
    - Interim Report of the Attorney General's White Collar Crime Committee, 1977 (Box 54, Folder 19)
  - Strike Forces, 12.
    These files serve as an interesting follow-up to those on the subject in the U.S. Attorney section. The folders include correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clippings, notes and reports. Notably, these files contain the critique by the General Accounting Office of the necessity of Strike Forces and the subsequent correspondence regarding that opinion. This is not the last time there will be strike force files in this archive as the issue persists during his years as Attorney General of the United States.
    - Correspondence from Thornburgh, 1975-1977 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda to and from Thornburgh, 1975-1977 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - General Accounting Office, Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - General Accounting Office, Memoranda, March, 1976-January, 1977 (Box 55, Folder 4-5)
    - Thornburgh's notes regarding the General Accounting Office, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - Pittsburgh Strike Force, 1974-1976 (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Clark Mollenhoff's Articles regarding Thornburgh and Strike Forces, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - "War on Organized Crime Faltering: Federal Strike Forces Not Getting the Job Done," Report to the Congress by the Comptroller of the United States, March 17, 1977 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Issue References, 13.
    These files represent topics of interest to Thornburgh including published reports kept for reference. The folders are listed by topic and are followed by reports that are in chronological order. All items contain the familiar underlining and/or annotations by Thornburgh.
    - Watergate, 1973-1976 (Box 55, Folder 11)
    - People in Politics, 1975-1977 (Box 55, Folder 12)
    - Oil/Energy, 1975-1976 (Box 55, Folder 13)
    - FBI, 1972-1977 (Box 55, Folder 14)
    - Legal Rights, 1975-1976 (Box 55, Folder 15)
    - Speeches by President Gerald Ford, 1975 (Box 55, Folder 16)
    - Bertram Zweibon et al., v. John N. Mitchell, Attorney General of the United States, June 23, 1975 (Box 55, Folder 17)
    - Law and the American Future, American Assembly on Law and the Changing Society II, Palo Alto, CA, June 26-29, 1975 (Box 55, Folder 18)
    - "A Report on the Pennsylvania Crime Commission," by the Pennsylvania Association of Bailbond Underwriters, December 31, 1975 (Box 55, Folder 19)
    - "The Criminal Use of False Identification," report of the Federal Advisory Committee on False Identification, DOJ, November, 1976 (Box 55, Folder 20)
    - "Evaluation of the Special Prosecutor's Office of Philadelphia," by Samuel Dash and Charles H. Rogovin, February 10, 1977 (Box 55, Folder 21)
    - News Clippings, Memos and Notes, 1975-1977 (Box 55, Folder 8)